<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the necessity of Revelation and an holy life deliver'd in a visitation-sermon at Guilford, October 7, 1697 / by William Whitfeld.</title>
            <author>Whitfeld, William, 1658-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65927</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26358</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09436577</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09436577</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43105</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65927)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43105)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1320:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the necessity of Revelation and an holy life deliver'd in a visitation-sermon at Guilford, October 7, 1697 / by William Whitfeld.</title>
                  <author>Whitfeld, William, 1658-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Holt for Tho. Bennet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Revelation --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Visitation sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43105:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43105:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF THE NECESSITY OF <hi>Revelation,</hi> and an <hi>Holy Life.</hi> Deliver'd in a <hi>Viſitation-Sermon,</hi> AT GUILFORD, <hi>October.</hi> 7. 1697.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM WHITFELD,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Holt,</hi> for <hi>Tho. Bennet,</hi> at the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:43105:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43105:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. L. 23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>— To him that ordereth his Converſation aright, will I ſhew the Salvation of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SEveral Verſes of this Pſalm, and likewiſe this of my Text, ſeem to be ſpoken by the Author in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God; being uſher'd in with this ſolemn Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to command our Attention, <hi>The Mighty God, even the Lord hath ſpoken;</hi> and my Text is introduc'd with this, <hi>Thus ſaith God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Pſalm it ſelf treats of calling all Mankind to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of rejecting the Jewiſh Sacrifices: From whence (as <hi>Cajet.</hi> obſerves) it is evident that the Time of Chriſt's Coming is here deſcrib'd, and that it is the Meſſiah who is this mighty Lord, brought in as an Interlocutor with the Prophet: He, who calls <hi>the Earth from the riſing of the Sun to the going down thereof,</hi> ſending his Summons forth, far beyond the Jewiſh Nation and <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law. All which ſeems peculiar to the Promulgation of the Goſpel, which was to take in all the Heathen <hi>for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43105:3"/>of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>the uttermoſt Parts of the Earth for his Poſſeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if from the Perſon chiefly concern'd in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Pſalm, we are to learn what is meant by the Salvation of God mention'd in my Text, it is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of that Redemption, which was extended to all Mankind by Jeſus Chriſt: If from the Perſon that ſpeaks in my Text, we may know who is to give us the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this Salvation, it is God himſelf who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to do it: And laſtly, if the ordering our Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aright, be propos'd as a Condition neceſſary for this Salvation being ſhew'd unto us, we may be aſſur'd that the Foundation of the Knowledge is to be laid in a Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Holy Life: Which are the ſeveral Parts that I intend to ſpeak to in my following Diſcourſe, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</p>
            <p n="1">I. That it is moſt worthy of the Salvation of God, that it be underſtood of the General Redemption of Mankind by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That the Knowledge of this Salvation is above the reach of Natural Reaſon; and not to be attain'd but by Revelation from God.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That it is an Holy Life, which will render us the moſt capable of receiving this Knowledge from God.</p>
            <p n="1">I. It is moſt worthy of the Salvation of God, that it be underſtood of the General Redemption of Mankind by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Both in the Old and New Teſtament (as the Seventh Article ſaith) Everlaſting Life is offer'd to Mankind by Chriſt, who is the only Mediator between God and Man. And <hi>there is none other Name under Heaven given among
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43105:3"/>Men whereby we may be ſaved, neither is there Salvation in any other.</hi> Nevertheleſs, before the <hi>Fulneſs of Time was come, wherein God ſent forth his Son to redeem them that were under the Law,</hi> this Knowledge was confin'd to very narrow limits; to a Nation exceedingly ſmall in proportion to the Inhabitants of all the Earth, and very inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble likewiſe in reſpect of the large Empires of the World, which extended their Dominions wide, together with the knowledge of many uſeful Sciences, by which they civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized a great part of Mankind.</p>
            <p>The Revelation beſides was dark, even where it was beſt known; particularly as to the Reſurrection of the Dead, which is the Anchor of our Hope after this Life, (the glad Tidings of Reward to the Good, and the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Puniſhment of the Wicked:) as alſo by reaſon of the ambiguity of the Law under Types and Shadows of things to come; which repreſented a Salvation to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven many Ages after by this general Redeemer, who was not commonly believ'd in by the Jews before his Coming, nor known by them when he appear'd.</p>
            <p>Such was the Knowledge of the Salvation of God (nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and obſcure) before the Coming of Chriſt; which now is reach'd out unto all Mankind by our Meſſiah, <hi>who is ſet for a Light to the Gentiles, and for Salvation unto the Ends of the Earth.</hi> Now is this Salvation perfected in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>in whom God hath reconcil'd the World unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi> And now is the Knowledge of it clearly manifeſted, <hi>ſince the Day-ſpring from on high hath viſited the World, to give Light to them that ſat in Darkneſs, and Knowledge of Salvation unto his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this ſuffice to ſhew in ſhort, that it is moſt worthy of the Salvation of God to be underſtood of this General Redemption, which is extended and manifeſted to all the Race of Mankind in Jeſus Chriſt; for Salvation was not to be had in any other, but in Him it was compleated, and perfectly known at his Coming. And this, we may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43105:4"/>is that Salvation promis'd in my Text, to be ſhewn unto us by God, if we ſhall order our Converſation aright; in which we may aſſure our ſelves, that without an Holy Life we are not fit to be inſtructed by God; and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Inſtruction from God, we are not able to attain the knowledge of his Salvation. For,</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Knowledge of this Salvation is above the reach of Natural Reaſon, and not to be attain'd but by Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from God.</p>
            <p>I will not diſpute how far our Natural Reaſon, unaſſiſted by Revelation, can lead us on in our way to the knowledge of God's true Worſhip, and to the attainment of eternal Happineſs; but ſhall take it for granted, that our Faith in Chriſt Jeſus is now become requiſite to Salvation; and that in all its neceſſary Doctrines it was not fully known, either to the wiſeſt of the Heathens, or to the beſt of the Jews, before it was revealed by God.</p>
            <p>And our Natural Reaſon is the ſame now as heretofore, and can ſhew us nothing new in this Diſquiſition, but as it ſhall pleaſe God to declare his Will concerning it: So that, if any things ſhall remain ſtill unreveal'd by God, or made known by him but in part, tho' a <hi>Socrates,</hi> a <hi>Plato,</hi> or an <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſhould at this day ſet themſelves to enquire into them, their Natural Knowledge could carry them no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now than it hath done of old; nor even <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith him, without a more expreſs Revelation from God.</p>
            <p>Now of this Nature I take to be that <hi>hidden Wiſdom</hi> of Almighty God, by which he hath ordained the great Work of our Redemption; ſeveral Articles whereof (warranted by the Apoſtles of Chriſt) we call the Myſteries of the Chriſtian Faith. Concerning which St. <hi>Paul</hi> (the moſt Learned Apoſtle, inſpired by God in a moſt eminent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and ropt up into the third Heavens) doth complain, that in this Life <hi>We know but in part, we ſpeak and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43105:4"/>as Children: We ſee</hi> (God and Divine Myſteries) <hi>thro' a Glaſs, darkly.</hi> We know but in <hi>part;</hi> becauſe God hath reveal'd them only in <hi>part,</hi> only in general, that there have bin ſuch Wonders wrought for our Redemption (which therefore we do believe) without declaring any thing of <hi>his hidden Wiſdom</hi> in their wonderful Production; which therefore when we ſpeak of, we ſpeak and underſtand as Children.</p>
            <p>Indeed, our knowledge in theſe things is much enlarg'd by the Revelation of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>who hath brought Life and Immortality to light;</hi> but yet there are ſtill remaining many <hi>Myſteries</hi> in the Work of our Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, far above the reach and capacity of our Natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to comprehend; which in this Life, we muſt content our ſelves to view only <hi>in a Giaſs, darkly,</hi> and not expect to behold them <hi>now,</hi> as we ſhall <hi>hereafter, Face to Face, and to ſee as we ſhall be ſeen,</hi> And it is the high Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of the Goſpel, that we may behold theſe Wonders of the Lord in <hi>this Glaſs,</hi> which the <hi>Law</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaith) look'd upon thro' a Veil: but it is <hi>our</hi> advantage to ſee thoſe Promiſes of God <hi>fulfilled,</hi> which our Forefathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held at a great diſtance from their Completion, and by the Light of Prophecy only (which <hi>ſhone in a dark place</hi>) or elſe thro' Types and Figures.</p>
            <p>But ſince it pleaſed God to require ſo ſtrong a Proof of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith that <hi>(hoping even against Hope, and not ſtaggering at the Promiſe of God thro' unbelief) He rejoyc'd to ſee the day of the Lord;</hi> and <hi>He ſaw it</hi> (even thro' this thick and gloomy Veil) <hi>and was glad;</hi> much more reaſonably may God expect from us, that <hi>we ſhould now be fully perſwaded, that what he hath promiſed, he hath been able alſo to perform;</hi> ſince it is given to us to ſee the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances of our God; to adore his Goodneſs in the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all his Promiſes, and in the completion of his Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to read the Myſteries of our Redemption in the Goſpels of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:43105:5"/>
            <p> And this Information not coming otherwiſe unto us, but from the Reveal'd Word of God, gives us a ſure Ground for our Belief (and for our <hi>Knowledge</hi> likewiſe) in theſe Myſteries; in which we cannot, with any ſhadow of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, complain, that we have not a good Foundation for our Faith; no more being requir'd to be believ'd concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, but as much as is Reveal'd of them by God; nor any thing farther neceſſary to be known of them, but what is declar'd by him; nor otherwiſe than as he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd.</p>
            <p>In this aſſurance we ſtand unmov'd againſt all vain Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions <hi>of the impoſſibility of there being any ſuch Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the Chriſtian Religion, and of our own incapacity to believe things which our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding cannot comprehend.</hi> Which aſſertions proceed from a bold, but miſtaken Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy; ignorant of the great Power of God; and not rightly diſtinguiſhing between the meaſure of Knowledge, ſufficient for Faith, and for Demonſtration; nor knowing, that where the Veracity of the Affirmer, and the Power of the Author of any Miracle are unqueſtionable, there we have a good Authority to believe his Relation of any thing, tho' it ſhall be wonderful, and far above our Capacity to comprehend.</p>
            <p>Now what God hath affirm'd, we have this reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and as far as we are capable of apprehending the Truth of a Propoſition in which any Myſtery is revealed by him, ſo far the Myſtery becomes a neceſſary object of our Faith; and we may be ſaid to underſtand enough of it, to <hi>believe,</hi> even when we cannot comprehend the manner and way by which it was produc'd; which (when they are not Reveal'd) we ſay remain a Myſtery ſtill; and when they are Reveal'd, they are often ſo likewiſe, being above our Underſtanding, in as much as the Power that wrought, is infinitely ſuperiour to all our Faculties of Reaſoning.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:43105:5"/>
            <p> For Example. In the Incarnation of Chriſt, becauſe God hath declar'd this in the Goſpel, it is therefore an Article of the Chriſtian Faith; but becauſe the incomprehenſible Union of the two Natures (of perfect God and perfect Man) is not ſhewn, and would have far ſurpaſs'd all our Knowledge, if it had been Reveal'd; it is therefore (as the Apoſtle ſaith) a <hi>Great Myſtery without all Controverſie, God manifest in the Fleſh.</hi> Nevertheleſs we may ſay, that we have ſome Notion in our Minds of what we believe herein; for the Truth of this Propoſition, <hi>God took upon him the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Man</hi> (being there is no contradiction in the Terms) may be conceiv'd in our Minds. And ſince we can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Truth of this Myſtery, and have a full aſſurance likewiſe of the Truth of that, which the God of all Power and Truth hath declar'd, we may affirm, that we do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what we believe, in this great Article of our Faith, and that we have a ſufficient meaſure of Knowledge for our Belief, and we may ſhew the Reaſons why we do believe it.</p>
            <p>It is, I know, impoſſible for the Eye of Natural Reaſon to look clearly and ſtrongly into the Works and Counſels of Almighty God; but this can be no Objection either againſt our apprehending the Truth of theſe Works and Counſels ſo far as they ſhall be Revealed; nor can the weakneſs of of our Underſtanding be any hindrance to our believing them, after they have been declar'd by God. For Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, It will not be deny'd, I ſuppoſe, that Almighty God hath Created this World out of Nothing; and we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive what we mean, when we profeſs in our Creed, that we do believe it; But our Belief and Knowledge of this muſt depend upon the Authority of <hi>Revetation,</hi> and not upon the ſtrength and powers of <hi>Natural Reaſon;</hi> for from <hi>this</hi> we can have no Idea in our Minds of this beautiful Frame, produc'd to be, and ariſing up from the Term of not Being; but we have from <hi>that</hi> an aſſurance of the Truth of it. We do in like manner agree in believing the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43105:6"/>Omnipotence of our Creator; but what Notion can <hi>our</hi> narrow Underſtanding receive of the ubiquity and pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his Preſence?</p>
            <p>Now, if theſe things do far exceed all the Limits and Powers of Natural Reaſon, more eſpecially ſo doth the wonderful Myſtery of our Redemption by our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt (the greateſt Work by far of God's Power and Love to Mankind;) which in its full extent can never lye within the compaſs of Human Knowledge, nor ever become <hi>naturally</hi> the Object of it; being that, which <hi>neither Eye hath ſeen, nor Ear heard, nor could it ever have entred into the Heart of Man,</hi> without a particular Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation from God: From whence alone it is, that we come to know the truth of this Myſtery, and to apprehend in ſome meaſure, what is meant by the words of a Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein we profeſs our belief of a thing far above our Comprehenſion; and from whence we have, in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the ſame Notion of all the moſt marvellous workings of God's Love for the compleating our Redemption; which are, and will continue to be Myſteries, ſo long as our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is <hi>Finite,</hi> and not commenſurate to the Power of an <hi>Almighty Being,</hi> and <hi>Infinite</hi> Spirit, whoſe <hi>Mercies,</hi> as well as <hi>Judgments,</hi> are unſearchable, and his Mightineſs to ſave, paſt finding out.</p>
            <p>This may ſerve to ſhow in general, the inſufficiency of many Cavils againſt ſeveral Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, rais'd moſtly by natural Men, who have the Pride to <hi>think above what is written:</hi> By one of which (meaſuring the whole Power of God by the Scale of his own Reaſon) it is affirm'd to be as <q>Abſurd to ſay, that God hath taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the Nature of Man, as that a Circle ſhould put on the nature of a Square.</q> 
               <hi>Spinoſ. Ep.</hi> 21. <hi>ad Oldenb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this is a Jeſt of the Philoſophers, 'tis very unbecoming the ſeriouſneſs of the Subject; and all good Men will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor his prophane Lightneſs in the main Article of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. But if it ſhall be ſaid in earneſt by him, 'tis a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43105:6"/>weak proof of his Judgment to argue from the Compariſon of a Square and Circle, whoſe Properties do lye within the compaſs of our Knowledge, to the Nature and Power of an Infinite Spirit, which we cannot comprehend: And to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the extent of God's Power and Love to Mankind, by a ſimilitude of things natural and circumſcrib'd, is truly abſurd.</p>
            <p>This may be one Inſtance, amongſt many, of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and pride of thoſe Men who ſet up without God to know and meaſure his Power, aſſaying without Revelation to penetrate into the Counſels of Divine Providence, and into the Myſteries of Man's Redemption, which even the Angels are deſirous to look into, but cannot. And when thou <hi>chargeſt thy Angels with Folly,</hi> what have we, O God, to rely upon without thy aſſiſtance! How uncertain a Guide to eternal Happineſs (purchas'd to Mankind by ſo many amazing Wonders of Infinite Love) is the ſingle Clue of Natural Reaſon! in it ſelf much deprav'd, and ſo unequally divided amongſt the Sons of Men, that it is not of the ſame ſtrength in any two Perſons Living! And yet (how weak ſoever it may be in ſome, and how unequal ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is in all) is it ſaid, that we muſt truſt to it for the knowledge of our Salvation, even before the Reveal'd Word of God.</p>
            <p>For, <hi>Socinus</hi> dares to ſay (and that more than once) <q>That tho' a thing were not only <hi>once,</hi> but oftentimes reveal'd in Holy Writ, he would not believe it, if it did not agree with his Reaſon, proceeding upon Natural Principles,</q> (for Reaſon, laying aſide Revelation, goes upon no other.) Now granting to <hi>Socinus,</hi> that his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought to be the only Rule and ſupreme Judge to <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> in theſe Matters about which he voucher it; yet the Underſtanding of all Men is not alike good: And therefore others who ſhall reaſon wrong, muſt believe falſely, and of conſequence hazard their eternal Happineſs, if they go upon the ſame Principle, and have no other Guide of their Faith
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43105:7"/>to Salvation. For <hi>Socinus</hi>'s Reaſon (tho' it ſhould be right) can never be a Rule to <hi>all;</hi> becauſe in thoſe Perſons unto whom it ſhall not appear <hi>ſo</hi> to be (and there are many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper'd Minds and differing Judgments in Mankind) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Man's Judgment can have no Power over their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</p>
            <p>And how then can this Principle build us up in Unity of Faith and Spirit, and in the Bond of Peace? and <hi>make us all to ſpeak the ſame thing, and to be perfectly joyn'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the ſame Mind, and in the ſame Judgment?</hi> to which the Apoſtle doth paſſionately exhort us <hi>in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Christ.</hi> We cannot be united in our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief by <hi>that,</hi> about which we ſhall perpetually contend, and in which we do ſo far differ from each other. But we may reaſonably ſuppoſe, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> had a greater Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and better Grounds to preſcribe Rules to our Faith than <hi>Socinus;</hi> and that in perſwading all Chriſtians to Unity, the Apoſtle knew that there was one General Principle in which they might all agree; a common Standard, which would regulate their Belief, and give Law to the diverſity of their Judgments, by delivering the ſame thing to their <hi>Faith,</hi> notwithſtanding the different Ways, and unequal Strength of Mankind in their Reaſoning. And if this Rule ſhall be no other than the Reveal'd Word of God, we may ſurely, with more ſafety, rely upon it for what is neceſſary to be known of our Salvation, than upon <hi>Socinus</hi>'s Reaſon, or upon our own.</p>
            <p>For it is certainly more becoming the Truth of God, and more ſecure for Mankind, that their Belief (upon which depends their everlaſting Happineſs) ſhould rather be foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon that which is ſtable, and for ever fix'd (as his moſt Holy Word is) than upon the ſagacity of Humane Reaſon, which varies, and encreaſes, and declines with Age, in all parts of which Salvation is alike neceſſary. It is moſt befitting the Juſtice of God, and moſt equitable to Mankind, that their knowledge of Salvation ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43105:7"/>from thence, wherein they all have a common Right and an equal Poſſeſſion; as they all have (or ought to have) in the Scriptures, who are to be judg'd by them; tho' unequal to each other in the ſtrength of their Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and differing much in the natural Endowments of their Mind. But Juſtice and Equity will plead for us, that this Knowledge ſhou'd reſt in ſomething wherein we are all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Partakers, as we all are of the Reveal'd Word of God; and in ſomething, wherein no Man excels his Brethren, as no Man <hi>naturally</hi> doth in the Power of believing the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, nor (with Grace) in his Abilities of obeying God's Commands to lead an Holy Life, and to order his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation aright.</p>
            <p>And this ſeems to be the diſtinguiſhing Character of the Salvation of God by Jeſus Chriſt, as we may preſume to infer from our bleſſed Saviour's paſſing by the Scribes and Phariſees, and Preaching his Goſpel chiefly to the Poor and Unlearned; where, not acuteneſs in Arguing, and large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Knowledge, but Probity of Life, and Humility of Mind were the proper Vertues that fitted them of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to be the firſt and the readieſt Receivers of the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God. And it is very remarkable that the Croſs of Chriſt, which brought Redemption and Salvation to the Souls of theſe Men, prov'd immediately after to the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Greeks</hi> Fooliſhneſs; for they ſought Wiſdom, but theſe the Kingdom of God; their Philoſophy taught them to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Belief of nothing which was not fetch'd from ſelf-evident Principles, and from thence deduc'd into demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration; and therefore no ſooner did they hear St. <hi>Paul preach of the Reſurrection of the Dead,</hi> but <hi>they</hi> (as ſome amongſt us do) <hi>Marked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of our Holy Faith, they receiv'd them with Contempt, being harden'd by their Pride a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt acknowledging any thing too ſublime for their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, or believing any thing which was not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with their fancied Schemes of Arguing: But as to the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43105:8"/>
               <hi>Duties</hi> of our Religion which lay plain and obvious to the meaneſt Capacity, <hi>Theſe</hi> were overlook'd by the high-minded Philoſophers; their <hi>Heads</hi> were warm with <hi>Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> but not ſo their <hi>Hearts</hi> with <hi>Charity;</hi> they train'd and exercis'd their <hi>Reaſon,</hi> (as they proudly imagin'd) but it was at the expence of their <hi>Humility;</hi> and ſo together with the loſs of the Goſpel-Duties, they made Shipwrack of the Chriſtian Faith, and ſpent their time in nothing elſe (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>but to tell and to hear ſome new thing.</hi> Which brings me to my laſt particular, to ſhew,</p>
            <p n="3">III. That it is an Holy Life which will render us the moſt capable of receiving this Knowledge. For to him that ordereth his Converſation aright, <hi>ſhall</hi> be ſhewn <hi>the Salvation of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this may ſeem to raiſe the Objection ſtill higher a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us; inaſmuch as that ſprightly Sence and Faith in the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt are not to be reconciled: To be a true Believer is to quit our Reaſon; to be <hi>ſeriouſly</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is to be ſunk <hi>deep</hi> in Melancholy, or prejudic'd by E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, or weaken'd with Age: 'Tis ſome way or other (they tell us) by impairing or prepoſſeſſing the Judgment, and therefore we declaim ſo much againſt the uſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in our diſquiſitions of Religion.</p>
            <p>It would be a moſt vain attempt to argue againſt the true uſe of Reaſon in any thing, but more eſpecially abſurd would it prove, to baniſh it from the Enquiries into the Chriſtian Faith, whoſe Truths have been Vindicated from the groſs Errors of Superſtition and Idolatry, by aſſerting to Humane Reaſon, and the Holy Scriptures, their right uſe and free Liberty. Yet this is the unjuſt Charge of our Adverſaries; taking their advantage from this Controverſie to object it moſt unrighteouſly againſt thoſe Divines of our Church, who have appeared upon all occaſions the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt, and (I may ſay) the moſt ſucceſsful Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt <hi>blind Obedience</hi> and <hi>implicit Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:43105:8"/>
            <p> But it may be granted, a ſuppoſe, to be no hindrance to Knowledge in <hi>general,</hi> to endeavour to aſſigh to Natural Reaſon its diſtinct Office, and to confine it to its own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Objects; and it wou'd prove the greateſt advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Human Learning <hi>in particular,</hi> to perform the ſame thing in its ſeveral Sciences. Now, in all <hi>theſe,</hi> it may be demonſtrated, that tho' all things fall under our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by the intermediate help of our Senſes, yet that there are many: things (thro' want of a fit Medium, or due diſtance) which cannot be rightly judged of, unleſs an appeal ſhall be made from our Senſes unto our Reaſon. And the <hi>ſame</hi> Subordination that there is in our Senſes to our Reaſon, may be ſaid to be in our Reaſon to Revelation, where it is own'd. For as in the knowledge of things Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, we cannot be ſatisfied and determin'd by the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from <hi>Senſe</hi> alone; but our Mind <hi>reſts</hi> in a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration from our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> notwithſtanding it may ſeem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to our Senſes: ſo in matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> being led to the knowledge of God's Word by our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal from its <hi>final Judgment</hi> to the higher authority of <hi>Revelation</hi> in all the Myſteries which that ſhall declare; and herein doth our Faith acquieſce, notwithſtanding the Word of God ſhall propoſe to our Belief great Wonders, ſeemingly diſagreeable to our Reaſon. Now in the one, we do not reject our Senſes, tho' we are not determin'd by them in the <hi>laſt Reſort,</hi> nor do we in the other reject our Reaſon; but we make uſe of <hi>both</hi> in gaining the Knowledge proper for them to comminicate within their reſpective Spheres, and proceed from thence, in referring the ſeveral Objects to be judg'd and determin'd at their right Bar; the Objects of Science by Reaſon, and the Objects of Faith by Revelation, with ſubmiſſion to the Sentence which ſhall there be pronounc'd upon each.</p>
            <p>And herein, if we may argue from the Judgments of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God (which are unſearchable by Human Reaſon) to the Myſteries of our Redemption, that which <hi>Salvian</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:43105:9"/>ſaith of our Submiſſion to the Juſtice of Divine Providence, may be fitly applied concerning the Reſignation of our Reaſon to the Revelation of God. <q>That thing (ſays <hi>Salvian</hi>) is not therefore not juſt, which God hath brought upon me, becauſe I cannot penetrate into the Method of its Equity; for as God is more than Man's Reaſon, ſo that thing ought to be unto me more than Reaſon, which I know proceeds from God.</q> It is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>God</hi>'s Reaſon, tho' not to <hi>Mine;</hi> and becauſe his Knowledge, and Wiſdom, and Providence do infinitely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs my Knowledge, and Wiſdom, and Reaſon, I ſubmit; becauſe God hath done it, it is juſt; becauſe God hath ſaid it, it is true.</p>
            <p>Now in all theſe Matters a ſound Mind is certainly one of the greateſt Bleſſings from Heaven, and never more needful than to paſs a right Judgment upon things of this Moment. Nor can an Inquiſitive Head be ever imploy'd to better purpoſe, than in examining what the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpel is, and what is reveal'd by God. For (as I have ſaid) our Reaſon brings us to the knowledge of that which is Reveal'd; to which I may add, that a ſound Mind is never at odds with true Religion; that is, a Mind poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd with Humility and Innocence of Life, and a ſtedfaſt relyance upon the Word of God; which are the Mediums thro' which our Reaſon is to judge of all things Reveal'd by Him. Without <hi>theſe Qualifications,</hi> Fancy and Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation too often uſurp the place of good Judgment and ſolid Reaſon; and not ſeldom doth it happen, that the moſt pregnant Parts, when accompanied with Prophaneneſs, and Pride, and Impiety, ſerve only to ſet the Owners of them ſo much the farther out of their way from ſerious Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Divine Truths.</p>
            <p>For the underſtanding of theſe things doth not ariſe ſo much from high Speculations, as from Conſcientious Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and receives Improvement from keeping the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God. And as to every Science, a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43105:9"/>Genius and aptitude are requir'd in the Learner, ſo there is to this, Piety, Humility, and Uncorruptneſs of Life al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways neceſſary; without which, <hi>Knowledge puffeth up</hi> (as the Apoſtle of Chriſt telleth us) <hi>but will never edifie;</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to <hi>our Faith we add Vertue, and</hi> then, (and after that) <hi>Knowledge to Vertue:</hi> And even ſtill we muſt be adding to our Knowledge; adding unto it <hi>Temperance, Patience, God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, Brotherly Kindneſs and Charity. For if theſe things be in you and abound, they will make you, that you ſhall neither be barren nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. But he that lacketh theſe things</hi> (he the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>is blind,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.5.</p>
            <p>Indeed a full and clear perception of all the great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of our Redemption is never to be attain'd in this Life, being (as we may humbly preſume) reſerv'd to make up the greateſt part of our Beatitude in Heaven, nor even in that Eſtate ſhall the knowledge of all Men be equal, but proportion'd to the Capacity of the Veſſel; yet theirs we may reaſonably believe will have the moſt degrees of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, whom exalted Love and eminent Piety ſhall place in the higheſt Stations of Glory; and that the ſame Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues will in the beſt manner prepare and enlarge our Souls in this Life, for the Reception of all Heavenly Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>For a Good Man Experiences, that a Life ſpent in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Integrity, tends more to advancing his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Juſt one that inhabits Eternity,</hi> than Memory or Wit: He finds that Chaſtity, Temperance, and Purity in Heart do beſt diſpoſe his Soul, to receive a moſt lively Impreſſion of the God of all Holineſs: Univerſal Charity will diſplay upon our Minds the brighteſt Rays of Infinite Mercy: A conſtant, regular Worſhip in the Houſe of God, and the Returns which are made by him unto our daily Prayers, will ſhew us <hi>truly</hi> God's Goodneſs: And Laſtly, a Worthy Receiving of the Holy Communion will make us one with Chriſt, and Chriſt with us. This is to order our Converſation aright, and from this Station God hath promis'd to ſhew us his Salvation.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:43105:10"/>
            <p> I will conclude with ſome Conſiderations upon what hath been ſaid by way of Application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we are firmly ſecure of our true Knowledge of the Salvation of God, in the Faith of that Church which we do profeſs; Let us then keep this Faith in Purity of Heart, and true Holineſs of Life, without which no Man ſhall ever ſee the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If any Man is doubtful, amidſt the many Diſputes which do at this time wound the Chriſtian Religion, and break the Bond of Peace; If he is ſerious in his Enquiries after that Knowledge which is to lead him to Eternal Life, Let him then in the ſincerity of his Heart make this Trial; and, from a good Life, begin his ſearches after the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Salvation of God. Let Piety, Humility, Integrity, and Charity, be the Foundation upon which he builds a true Faith; and let him firmly believe, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully practice all that his Conſcience ſhall tell him God hath aſſuredly revealed and commanded, with a Mind free from prejudice, and ready to receive greater Meaſures of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as they ſhall be tender'd unto him from his Word. And for his Encouragement, he hath an inſtance in the Scripture of a good and holy Man, who came to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Salvation of God this way. <hi>Cornelius a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Man, one that feared God with all his Houſe, which gave much Alms to the People, and prayed to God always.</hi> His Prayers were heard, and his Alms had in remembrance in the ſight of the Lord; and he was ſoon after this ſhown the Salvation of God: From his ſincere performance of that which he did know to be God's Will, he was led on ſucceſsfully to the Knowledge of the Salvation of Jeſus Chriſt, of which he was ignorant; from a Proſelyte of the Gate, to be baptized into the Chriſtian Faith. <hi>And of a truth God is no Reſpecter of Perſons; but in every Nation, He that feareth God, and worketh Righteouſneſs, is accepted with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43105:10"/> 3. Wickedneſs of Life is the moſt fatal ſtep to Infidelity, and ſets us at the greateſt diſtance from this Knowledge of the Salvation of God.</p>
            <p>For Vice, as the Platoniſts obſerve, doth much cloud and weaken the Underſtanding, and ſhews its Maſtery and Dominion over the Mind by the Captivity it hath brought it under. And without this Natural Incapacity (if I may ſo call that Inability which proceeds from the Corruption of Nature,) impure Minds are very improper Judges of true Holineſs, and the wicked Liver inſufficient for the Salvation of God; from the Knowledge of which he ſeems to be particularly excluded; God ſaying unto <hi>Him</hi> in the Pſalm of my Text, <hi>What hast thou to do to declare my Statutes? Or that thou ſhould'ſt take my Covenant in thy Mouth? Whereas thou hateſt Inſtruction, and caſteſt my Words behind thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The wicked Man hateth Inſtruction:</hi> Even He, that is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the much-boaſted Maſter of right Reaſon, and only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Seaarcher after Truth; He that ſets by himſelf as the beſt qualified for Knowledge, becauſe he doubts and diſputes every thing, treading ſervily in no Man's ſteps, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly freeing his Mind from prejudice, and raiſing his Underſtanding above all that have gone before him. But ſtill the wicked Man <hi>caſteth the Words of God behind him;</hi> the Words which God hath revealed to inſtruct him in His Faith, and to direct him in an Holy Life; <hi>and he hateth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, hating</hi> (as the Pſalter tranſlates it) <hi>to be reform'd. For thou givest thy mouth to Evil,</hi> (ſaith God;) <hi>when thou ſawest a Thief then thou conſentedſt with him, and haſt been Partaker with Adulterers:</hi> And with theſe Qualifications, thou ſetteſt up for a Reviler of Chriſt Jeſus, and a Director in Religion.</p>
            <p>God forbid that this ſhould be charg'd upon all Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers! Many of which have Modeſty, and many, I hope,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43105:11"/>Vertue, whom God, I truſt, in his Mercy will bring home to himſelf in his appointed time. But yet the Obſervation which <hi>Grotias</hi> makes upon the <hi>Nataral Man,</hi> from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the Greek Philoſophers, (moſt of which Hiſtory delivers down as unclean and impure in their Lives.) we find too often verified: It being a moſt juſt Judgment of Almighty God, that the Deſpiſers of his Word ſhould <hi>walk in the Luſts of their own Hearts,</hi> and be given up to the <hi>Vices,</hi> as well as to the <hi>Errors</hi> of corrupt Nature; to ſhew them, how uncertain a Guide they have to their <hi>Salvation,</hi> which they experience to be ſo far deprav'd in their <hi>Morals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of all ſuch, we may be bold to ſay (whoſoever they are that ſhall join Infidelity and a vicious Life together,) that <hi>their</hi> Enquiries into <hi>Divine Truths</hi> are vain and abſurd. 'Tis no wonder to hear <hi>them</hi> ſtrenuouſly oppoſing the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of a ſuture State; for it is neceſſary that <hi>they</hi> either ſtifle the Thoughts of <hi>that,</hi> or elſe forſake the Enjoyment of their preſent Pleaſures. And 'tis no matter how <hi>they</hi> wreſt and pervert, or wholly deny the Written Word of God; which being <hi>denied,</hi> extinguiſhes the dread of Puniſhments to come; and being perverted, takes away the Eternity of their Torments. 'Tis no more than we may expect, to find them diſputing againſt the Eternal Law of Good and Evil: For theſe are the Barriers fix'd againſt their Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which they wou'd fain have remov'd: And we may hear them (but with Horror) daily blaſpheming the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of Jeſus Chriſt, God bleſſed for evermore; whom they ſhall find their Judge at the laſt Day, but never their Saviour. Prophaneſs and wilful Ignorance in theſe Men ſerve them for Pandars to their Luſts in this preſent Life, and without ſevere Repentance, they are the Pledges likewiſe of the Outer Darkneſs and Blaſphemings, which ſhall be their Portion and Torments hereafter.</p>
            <p>O that God in his Infinite Mercies, may forgive us theſe great Sins of Prophaneſs in Holy Things, and Impurity of Life join'd together! (Sins which we ſee too cloſely united, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43105:11"/>too much triumphant!) O that in his Goodneſs He may preſerve the yet Innocent and Faithful in their Integrity, Faith, and Vertue! and open their Eyes to diſcover the Deceits, and to avoid the Luſts of theſe impious Wretches! And may that good and gracious God, whoſe Mercies and Long Suffering are boundleſs, give unto themſelves a time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Repentance, before he calls them to Judgment!</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As to our ſelves, my reverend Brethren, ſhall I call it our <hi>Affliction,</hi> or our <hi>Happineſs,</hi> that we have <hi>theſe</hi> Perſons our implacable Adverſaries? It is to our unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Grief, that there will always be ſuch Men (and that this Age and Nation do too much abound with them) Enemies to the Religion of Chriſt, and to their own Souls: But it is I think to our <hi>Honour,</hi> that the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> and our <hi>Fanction,</hi> have one Common Adverſary, and that the Revilers of the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> are likewiſe <hi>Blaſphemers</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>To make our Glory the greater, we will be ſure (by the Bleſſing of Almighty God) to adorn our Profeſſion with an unblameable and upright Converſation, the true ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work of all our Knowledge in that Salvation, which we are to teach others, and to attain ourſelves.</p>
            <p>And herewith let us not be diſcourag'd! They boaſt much of the ſtrength of their Reaſon; I wiſh it were ſound and true, (for then there would be no Cauſe of difference;) but we, I truſt, have <hi>that</hi> on our ſide; experieneed from our Education, how to wield the Weapon; and, from our Knowledge in the Scriptures, where to let it fall in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Faith: To which let us add (what our Holy Function indiſpenſably requires,) a good Life, and our faithful Labours in the Word of God; our beſt Security for our Knowledge in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Let theſe be our ſtrong Hold, our Rock of Defence, and our Caſtle, in which we will truſt! from which nothing ſhall ever make us to recede, or draw us out beyond our Lines: Not the <hi>Vanity</hi> of trying our Strength in New
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43105:12"/>Schemes of Divinity; not the <hi>Hardyneſs</hi> of rejecting the Receiv'd and Eſtabliſh'd Terms of the Church of Chriſt; not the <hi>Deceitfulneſs of Philoſophy</hi> to forſake the Word of God. And then with all aſſurance, we may appeal to the good and unprejudiced part of Mankind, which is the ſafeſt Guide to the Knowledge of the Salvation of God, <hi>Reaſon with</hi> the Goſpel, or <hi>Reaſon without it.</hi> It is the Cauſe of God in which we are engaged, and the Redemption of all Faithful Chriſtians through the Blood of Chriſt, for which we contend: <hi>Let us therefore play the Men for our People, and for the Cities of our God!</hi> But let God himſelf be the Director in the Methods of his own Salvation. <hi>And the Lord do that which ſeemeth him good!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this be <hi>Prieſt-Craft, may our Right Hand never forget her Cunning!</hi> May our Studies be ſerious, our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours ſtrong, and our Prudence and Charity always exercis'd in it! That by it we may catch Men, even them (if it ſhall be the good Pleaſure of Heaven,) who uſe <hi>their Craft</hi> for the deſtruction of thoſe Souls for which Jeſus Chriſt died.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now, O Lord, behold their Threatnings and Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings! In thy Mercy renew a right Spirit within them! And grant unto thy Servants that with all Boldneſs they may ſpeak thy Word in Truth and Soberneſs!</hi> That with Conſtancy they may teach that Faith <hi>which was once deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd unto the Saints!</hi> That they may ſtand up in defence of thy Holy Scriptures, not without much Blood, reſcu'd out of the Hands of <hi>unreaſonable</hi> Men by our Forefathers of the Reformation. And of thy Grace, add to theſe Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Integrity of Life, and Purity of Manners in thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants which wait at thy Altar! So ſhall we be able, O Lord, by the Soundneſs of our Doctrine, and Holineſs of our Lives, both <hi>to exhort and convince Gainſayers,</hi> and to ſhew forth the Salvation of God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43105:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
